This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Bob Nystrom.
Bob Nystrom is a software engineer at
Google working on the Dart programming
language.
Before falling in love with programming
languages and compilers, he was a game
developer, UI programmer, pixel artist,
and computer animator. He's also the
author of Crafting Interpreters and Game
Programming Patterns, a college dropout,
and a fairly decent cook.
Bob,
Bob, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. Is there anything I missed in
your bio that you'd like to add?
No, I think that's all the highlights.
Everything else about me is strictly
less interesting than those points.
And is a college dropout a good or a bad
thing?
I mean, for me it's probably not
necessarily a good thing, but I do like
mentioning it because I know that
there's a certain number of people that
have imposter syndrome about their own
level of educational attainment. And,
you know, I've been super fortunate in
my career and I like being able to point
out that like, yeah, it's possible to be
a software engineer at Google even if
you don't have a college degree. So that
hopefully, I don't know, hopefully
people feel that doors are maybe a
little more open than they thought they
were.
Yeah, cuz sometimes you do get that
imposter syndrome because you haven't
done that bit or you haven't done the
masters or you haven't done the PhD.
Something I feel all the time. I think
we all suffer from it.
Yeah, I still wrestle with it at work
all the time.
I think one of the lessons I learned was
just give yourself a break. Somewhere I
read about something.
Cool. Thank you for that. So,
the show today is on Dart programming
language. And what we're going to do is
we're going to talk about why and when
it was created to understand when to use
it, its top three benefits,
where it can be used, and I did a
previous show with Tim Sneath on
Flutter, episode 437. So, we might
circle back and
Tim is great.
Yeah, he he actually put your name
forward as someone brilliant to talk to.
that how this happened?
You've got something to live up to.
Yeah, I I can promise you I won't do as
good a job of as Tim would, but I'll try
to be a tolerable second place.
Cool. I think we'll be fine. So, I'd
like to start with an overview of what
type of programming language Dart is
and its top three features and when we
should reach for it. So, the dart.dev
website, so that's the URL, dart.dev,
headline is
Dart is a client-optimized language for
fast apps on any platform. What does
that mean?
Oh, man, that is a nice brand summary.
So, the bits there are it's
cross-platform, right? So, it's not
targeting a single, you know, OS family
or something like Swift is.
And it's client-focused, which means,
you know, for me as a language designer,
I think it means two interesting things
that are kind of in opposition.
One of them is that it's a language
designed to run on hardware that the
programmer doesn't control, right? So,
if I'm using a language like, you know,
Ruby or Python on a server, and, you
know, I'm making uh
you know, a website or a service or
something, I generally control the
hardware, right? So, if my language is
slow, it's running on my machines
anyway, and I can throw more machines at
it, right? So, I have ways to sort of
balance cost and performance that are
under my control. But, if I'm for client
devices, I don't have that, right? Like,
if the language is slow, if the language
implementation is slow, then the
application is slow because it's running
on a machine that I can't make go any
faster, right? Like, if it's running on
someone's, you know, low-spec phone in a
developing country, if the language
compiles to slow code, that means that
app is is slow, right? So, being focused
on client applications means that
performance matters a lot.
That is a good answer.
This may not be the first time I've been
asked this question.
But there's a an interesting flip side
to it, too, which is that, you know, you
can think of client apps as like UIs,
right? Like we are a language for
building programming UIs in, right? And
I don't Have you Have you ever done UI
development before?
Yeah, I've done an app start to finish
that's on the app stores now using
Flutter and and Dart and
Okay, cool.
My business sponsored a SIP
implementation of Dart, an open-source
project that is really popular in the
only SIP Stockholm Dart.
So, I'm quite familiar with it. That's
why I wanted to do this show.
Yeah, so then you know what the
experience of like when you're doing UI
programming feels like where you're just
tweaking a lot of stuff, right? Like
there's a lot of sort of subjective
choices you're making about like layout
and sizes and positions and colors. And
you kind of need to just see that on
screen to get a feel for it.
And there's this very tight iteration
loop that you need, right? It's not
like, you know, if you're doing
low-level programming, sometimes you can
sit down and write 500 lines of code and
then run it and then see if everything
does what you want. But with UI, you
need this sort of incremental feedback,
which means the developer productivity
matters a lot, right? Like you need a
language that is pretty fast to compile
and reload and get things up and
running. Something that feels
lightweight and kind of scripty. Doesn't
feel like there's a lot of, you know,
ceremony.
And those two goals, being fast on the
user's machine but also being fast to
iterate on and being high-level and
productive, are, you know, they tend to
be in opposition, right? It's hard to
write a high-level language that
compiles to efficient code. And it's
hard to make a low-level language fun to
use. So, Dart, you know, our sort of
goal as a language is to to try to find
the kind of balance point between that.
Yeah, that's something I experienced in
our app where I could have done screens
and stuff, but it was so fast and the
the feedback was instant. You could
literally just play as you were and just
work through what you had in your head
because it was so such instant feedback.
That's something I really liked about
it.
Yeah, that's cool to hear.
You know, so before I was at Google, I
was a a game developer and you know, you
work with game programmers and game
designers and you know, there's this
sort of like numeric measure of
productivity of like, oh, well, how much
can you get done in a given day and like
that kind of matters, you know, at some
economic level or something. But the
thing that I really care about is like,
you know, I've watched people work and
if you give them a developer experience
that is smooth enough and fast enough,
there's a qualitative difference in what
it feels like to do that work and the
kind of work that you get out of it,
right? Like if it if it's enjoyable and
smooth and fast enough to iterate on the
thing you're working on, you'll try
stuff out. Like you'll make experiments.
You'll be like, let's see if this works
out and you will get to, I believe
you'll get to a better design than you
would if it was more effortful, right?
Like so it's not just that like yeah,
you ship faster. It's, you know, like I
think it it does affect the quality of
the thing you end up making.
Yeah, I can totally relate to that
because if you had an idea, you could
just instantly try it because you could
see it straight away.
And most nights when I was on, even if
you're not in your zone as it were,
you're up till 1:00 2:00 a.m. because
you can just try so many things and see
it straight away.
Yeah, it's such a cool feeling, right?
To sort of get lost in it, you know?
Yeah. So, why and when was Dart created?
It's quite old from program language's
point of view.
It has had a bit of a storied history.
So, we've been around
maybe 9 years.
Is that right? That sounds right.
Somewhere around there. We worked on it
for a while internally before we open
sourced it, but not that long. We open
sourced pretty early.
And then it was out there and didn't
have a lot of adoption for several years
and you know, we had to kind of pivot in
some ways and then when Flutter came
along, that was sort of the thing that
kind of picked us up, you know, I look
at Flutter as being sort of like Ruby on
Rails was for Ruby, right? Where like
Ruby It around for a long time before
Rails, but it wasn't, you know, you need
something like a killer app for a
language to really thrive and and
Flutter was for Dart.
Yeah, there's quite a few like those in
there. There's the Phoenix web framework
which is Elixir.
There's Laravel which is PHP and it just
seems to be
you like that framework and the language
just comes along with it.
Yeah, you know, it's a big ask to get
someone to learn a new programming
language, right? Like it it takes a lot
of work. It's a It's an investment in
cognitive resources that they don't get
to use on other stuff. And it's hard to
motivate people to do that unless it
takes them to somewhere that they can't
get to otherwise. So, if it's like
Objective-C where it's, you know, at the
time the only way to program for a
particularly desirable target, then
they'll learn it. Or if it's the only
way to use a particularly desirable
framework like Flutter or Rails, then
they'll learn it. But if you don't have
kind of anything that really, you know,
drags people over that chasm to get them
to learn it, then it's really, really
hard to get people to.
And how easy is it for someone to learn?
So, for example,
speaking about getting up to
productive state, if I can speak.
Rust, for example, has quite a
reputation of being difficult to get
because of certain concepts like borrow
checking and other things. But my
experience, correct me if I'm wrong,
it was pretty easy just to drop in
because it had quite a JavaScript-esque
feel. And then a Go lang or Go type feel
with the
static types if you wanted that and the
dynamic types. But I think what made it
really easy for me was the
sort of first-class integration with
Android Studio.
Oh, interesting. Okay. When you're
hacking on your Dart code, you're
usually doing it within Android Studio?
Oh, yeah. When I first started, I never
used it. Just the error prompting and,
you know, do this and click through to
the class to see what all the methods
and happy options are.
And the docs in the actual source code
of Dart are fantastic when you when you
get down to that level.
You know, one of the things I'm really,
you know, grateful is that we have a
team at part of the Dart team doing
static analysis and doing IDE
integration. And they're just great.
They're just super great people and they
you know, they just care so much about
having a good rich user experience when
you're working with the language.
So, all that stuff comes from them.
They're they're awesome.
So, you asked a question earlier about
like, you know, how easy is it to learn
Dart? And that's a really cool question
because
it's deeper than it sounds, right?
Because the question then is, well, easy
for whom, right? And there's interesting
trade-offs that you make there, right?
So, the the original designers of Dart,
their number one goal was to make a
language that's easy to learn for people
coming from JavaScript and Java. And
Dart looks a lot like JavaScript and
Java because of that, right? And it has
a lot of the same concepts, right? You
know, it's object-oriented,
you know, it's got classes, it's got
functions, it has the same basic kind of
C syntax that uh JavaScript and Java
have. So, you know, for that very large
pool of people, you know, the feedback
that we get, the data that we get from
user studies is that Dart is pretty easy
to pick up. But there's an interesting
trade-off there when you're a language
designer, which is like
the way to make a language easy to learn
is to make it similar to languages that
people already know, right? But if you
make it too similar, then then what's
the value proposition, right? You know,
why bother switching at all? So, there's
this tricky balancing act that we have
to do where we have to
make the language different in ways that
are positively compelling so that
there's a reason to learn it at all,
but at the same time it's sort of try to
minimize the negative difference from
other languages. It's a tricky balancing
act. And it's also tricky balancing
making it easy to learn for people
coming from certain other language
families versus, you know, maybe making
it easier to learn for Python
programmers or for people that have
never programmed at all, right? Like
each of those people has a different
perspective and targeting those groups,
you know, kind of pushes the language in
different directions.
Yeah, it depends what level you're at to
start.
You know, if you're seasoned in a couple
of languages or really know a certain
language, then
certain computer science concepts apply
to any language. And then it comes down
to the quality of the community
ecosystem that you're trying to figure
out, well,
how do I do this in Dart? Cuz I know how
to do it in Java or JavaScript or
another language.
Yeah.
So, I think we've touched on what other
languages are similar to Dart, which is
JavaScript. When should a programmer use
Dart,
say if they're not using Flutter?
You should use Dart all the time for all
of your programming needs, obviously.
It's a good question, you know, so one
level we are a general purpose language.
We have We ship with a command line VM
that has, you know, networking and file
system integration built into it kind of
like Node.js for JavaScript. So, you can
write, you know, command line apps,
services, servers, all sorts of stuff in
Dart. Almost all of our tools that we
ship with Dart are written in Dart. So,
our static analysis framework, our
compilers to JavaScript, you know, code
formatter, all that stuff, all that's
written in Dart. You know, I think it's
a pretty good general purpose language.
So, yeah, so short answer is use it for
all the stuff. But, we have, you know,
we do generally invest in it being a
client-side UI language to some degree,
you know, maybe at the expense of other
domains. And in particular, it's really,
really difficult to
compete with other languages when it
comes to writing, you know, servers and
services, that kind of stuff, you know,
web framework, back-end web framework
kind of stuff. Not really at the
language level, but at the ecosystem
level, right? Like if you're
you know, if you're writing a web
back-end in, you know, Ruby or Python or
Java, you know, there is already
bindings and mature libraries for every
single database and other,
you know, facility that you need. All
that stuff exists.
Yeah, it comes down to the libraries you
have access to and not having to start.
Yeah.
We're getting there with Dart. It's
growing, but you know, we're not as far
along there as languages that have, you
know, 20-year head start on us. So, that
ends up kind of being one of the
limiting factors. We are in some ways a
high-level language. You know, language
is garbage collected, memory safe. So,
the performance that we get is, you
know, is good. I feel good about it, but
it's probably not the best language for
stuff that it needs to either be very
low-level or very high performance,
right? So, you could you know, you can
write games in Dart, but you're probably
not going to write a triple-A game, and
you're probably not going to write like,
I don't know, a USB driver or something
in Dart where you need, you know, access
to raw memory, things like that.
But, you do have the
Is it the FFI?
Yeah, so we have FFI. We have pretty
nice C and C++ interrupt now.
So, yeah, you can do that. I mean, you
you could, but you know, there's sort of
like, you know, I think of every
language is kind of having, I don't
know, like a sort of grain to it.
Yeah. What was that foreign something
interface, wasn't it? FFI?
Yes. Yeah, foreign function interface.
Sorry,
Yeah, we did touch about that the show
with Tim Sneath. I'm going to start
moving us on to the next section
shortly.
Sure.
I just wanted to
touch on the top three benefits of Dart
in your experience.
Oh, man, compared to what?
I'm not going to give you the answer.
Oh, man.
So, I you know, I can tell you what I
particularly like about Dart. And I
should say that, you know, my
want to cheat, you can go on to the
front page of the dart.dev website.
Oh, it's it's more fun for me to
Yeah, you give me your three. That
That'll be fine.
Yeah. You know, I should say, you know,
so my role on the Dart team is I work
directly on the language. In some ways,
that means I'm a little removed from
what the average day-to-day Flutter
developer's user experience is like. You
know, I have a professional interest in
knowing what that world is like because
that's that's who I'm serving, but
that's, you know, I don't make Flutter
apps every day. So, I may not be the
best person to tell you, you know,
what's what's amazing about it, but I
can tell you, you know, what I like
about it. So, I like object-oriented
programming. I've been writing code for
3/4 of my life at this point now, and I
don't know, I'm super comfortable, you
know, when I have to write a large
program organizing it in terms of
classes. I think that works well for
programming in the large. I think it
works really, really well for UI
programming, but I also really like
functional programming. You know, I'm
very comfortable with closures and
higher-order functions and stuff like
that, and I think that's a really nice
way to model algorithms and
smaller-scale code, and Dart is one of
my favorite languages for combining
those two paradigms, where I feel like
both of those are sort of first-class
citizens in the language, and they
harmonize together well. So, I kind of
like the experience of like programming
the language. I don't know, I like
writing Dart code. I enjoy it. I feel
productive in it. And then kind of at
the the implementation level, you know,
the fact that we have hot reload is
pretty amazing, right? Like that you
can, you know, make changes to your
program and see the results of those
changes literally within milliseconds
without having to reboot your app and
without having to, you know, get back
into the state you were in is
incredible. You know, I used to be a
game developer, and you know, I can't
tell you how much of my life I have
spent restarting the game and then
having to like, you know, play it or,
you know, go into the debugger and set a
bunch of fields to try to get the game
back into the state that I was in before
I made some code change. And the fact
that, you know, we have a a VM that can
just do that is super cool.
Yeah, we're going to talk to on that in
the next section.
Oh, well then I shouldn't get ahead of
things.
I think we've got a good intro there.
There's some some things I've missed,
but we've pretty much crossed over them
in our initial chat. So, take the first
headline from the website, which is
optimized,
spelled with a Z, although it should be
spelled with an S.
Optimized for UI.
Now that we've had a good intro,
Mhm.
we'll go through those top three
benefits
that you didn't answer, but they're on
the website, so we'll let you off.
Sorry.
That's fine. So, Dart has the concept of
async await.
Oh, yeah. I could spend a lot of time
talking about that.
And isolate-based concurrency. That's a
nice sentence. The concept of async
await and isolate-based concurrency.
What the heck are these and why are they
important for user interfaces?
So, they're fairly separate from each
other. So, you can have one without the
other. So, Dart has these things called
isolates. I don't know where that word
came from. I don't know if it exists
outside of the Dart ecosystem, but they
are concurrency primitive, right? So,
they're a way of having multiple threads
running uh truly concurrently without
having the complexity and the overhead
of thread synchronization, right? So,
you know, concurrency is in a lot of
ways kind of like the holy grail of
programming languages where it doesn't
seem like anyone has found a silver
bullet for how to
let people use multiple cores
effectively
in a really nice usable programming
paradigm, right? Like, it seems like
every model for concurrency has
downsides. And isolates is one approach
to that. So, the way isolates work is
you can think of each of them as each
isolate is essentially a separate little
Dart program that is running
concurrently with the main Dart program.
And it is running truly concurrently on
different threads. So, it's just each
isolate is going off doing its thing.
And then we have these things called
ports that let you communicate between
them.
So,
you know, you get the the performance
benefits of multithreading, but you
don't have the maintainability nightmare
of shared memory multithreading. So,
each isolate has its own heap, and
they're not allowed to directly access
each other's memory. So, you can't get,
you know, races and concurrent updates
and all the sort of nightmares that you
get if you do raw low-level threaded
programming.
That's a really good explanation cuz I
just thought of them as threads,
but they sound more like message passing
actor.
Yeah, they're almost more like processes
and in particular they end up not
feeling quite like actors because I
think the blocking model is a little
different, but they are they're
actor-like, too. They're kind of similar
in that way.
I'm thinking like how Erlang and Elixir
do things and how it go
go routines work and
Yeah, actors is a probably a pretty good
way to think about it. They're a little
different from like Go and Go routines
because Go routines will block, right?
So, if you if you send something to a Go
routine
you will pause until the other thing is
ready to receive it if it's unbuffered.
I believe, I'm not a Go programmer.
Whereas isolates, they run
they really do sort of run concurrently
and you can't really like, you know, get
them to sort of halt. They're sort of,
you know, you can throw stuff at them,
but they will sort of run on their own.
So, they feel less kind of coordinated
and coupled together than something like
coroutines would.
And is this something that
Dart and Flutter just do in the
background or is it something you have
to think about and create isolates and
It is something you have to think about.
So, you you asked earlier like how does
this tie into sort of being optimized
for UI programming? So, one of the other
things
that is interesting about UI programming
and in particular UI programming on
mobile devices is that
your goal as an implementation is not
just to like get as much done as fast as
possible, right? You need to be able to
break up the work that the programming
language does into small enough pieces
such that you don't drop frames, right?
So, it's not just like you know like a
Java server program is doing this giant
batch of work over a terabyte of data
and once it's done it quits and then
you're just like all I care about is the
total execution time. If you're running
on a client device, you care about not
just the total execution time, but the
incremental performance, right? And
especially on a mobile device where
users expect to be able to touch and
drag stuff at 60 FPS and not drop
frames, that kind of incremental
performance matters. So, it comes into
play with concurrency because you have
one thread that is drawing, you know,
receiving user input and drawing the UI,
and if you do any expensive computation
on that thread, you will stop the UI,
right? You'll stop the UI from updating,
and the user experience is that is is
jank and dropped frames. So, having some
level of concurrency like isolates gives
you a way to take long-running
computation and push it onto another
thread so that the UI thread can keep
running and keep updating the UI.
And that's why you would need to be in
control of that because you're
telling the system what is going to take
a while.
Yeah. Yeah, in practice, you know, you
sort of need to know which things are
computationally heavy, and then, you
know, because isolates each have their
own memory and they don't share access
to memory, usually if you're doing some
heavy computation, that means you're
doing some computation over some data,
and you also need to think about like,
okay, how do I make sure that it's the
isolate that has that data, and that I'm
not just, you know, burning a bunch of
time sending data back and forth between
them two.
And how much control do you have
from the OS level because we've spoken
about not having control of the hardware
cuz that's the point of
client-optimized,
mhm, but if we're
putting things in these isolates because
it's taking a while,
what's the risk of the operating system
killing them off?
That's a good question. I don't know.
I mean, how long, you know, that just
depends on what you set on your phone, I
suppose, what Android's being tweaked on
or what iOS is doing.
Yeah, I
I guess so. This is outside of my area
expertise, sorry. I don't have a good
answer, but this is something that, you
know, so the Dart
the Dart implementation, the VM that,
you know, that we have that, you know,
that Flutter contains
basically implements isolates in terms
of
the threading primitives that the
underlying OS gives it, right? So, on
Android, it will use, you know, the
threading model that Android provides,
and iOS will do the same thing, and in
principle, it's the VM's job to
hide the differences between those OS's
as much as possible so that Dart
programmers just see this high-level
isolate concept and things work the way
they expect. In practice, you know, as
I'm sure you know, platform details leak
through, right? Like you can't always
encapsulate that stuff.
Yeah, there's usually some copy out,
isn't there?
There's always copy out, right?
I should just point out to the listeners
that because we've been talking about
Flutter, which is
generally to make your app for an iOS
device or Android device, or you can put
it on Windows or Linux, that's just why
I was talking about iOS and Android
there because when I think of Dart, I
think of those two platforms when it
works on lots of different platforms.
Yeah, I think, you know, the large
majority of our users now writing Dart
code are end up running it on Android
and iOS devices and then a decent
fraction of them running on the web with
their Dart code compiled to JavaScript.
Yeah, so we'll stick to those two if
something else comes up. And how does
this relate to async await? Does that
Oh man, how much time do we have?
Well, we've got maybe 3 minutes before I
need to move on to the next session, so
I should probably
Yeah.
A five A five-word answer for that one.
So because isolates are running
concurrently and you don't want to block
them,
you need a way to send a request to
another isolate and then have the code
pause until the response comes in. And
async await gives you a nice syntax for
doing that so that you get asynchronous
code that looks like blocking
synchronous code.
So if people haven't used Dart, maybe
because that's why they're listening to
this or they want some more in-depth
information,
the
language keywords await and async,
correct me here, basically sort of wrap
a block of code and you define it as
something like that. You
await an answer. Behind the scenes, is
that firing up a
some concurrency there or
It's a little complex. So the async
keyword basically just says it's a
modifier you put on the function that
says
in this function I'm going to be doing
stuff using await. I'm sort of opting
into that. And then when you use the
await keyword, it's a marker that you
put on an expression. What it does is it
basically splits the body of the
function in half at that point, and it
takes everything after the await and
wraps it in another closure. And then it
says,
"Evaluate the expression that I'm
awaiting for,
and then unwind the entire call stack
back to the scheduler.
And then when the thing that the that
I'm awaiting on, the expression that I'm
the value that I'm waiting for, when
that comes in at some point in the
future, run the remaining body of that
code, which has now been moved kind of
into a separate function. The technical
term for this is it's doing something
called it's transforming the
the body of the function into something
called continuation passing style, which
doesn't mean a lot to people that are
not compiler people. But basically what
it lets you do is it lets you have
multiple pieces of code that are kind of
ideally waiting for responses. It lets
you have all those kind of sitting out
there pending without taking up the
memory and the resources of having a
hardware thread. Because what happens
instead is that the call stack can
unwind for those, and you just have
closures that are waiting to be
evaluated at some point in the future.
That was a brilliant explanation. I love
how deep that was. But with the async
stuff, when
we're talking about wrapping something
in async,
Mhm.
the await is an option, isn't it?
Because you might just want to run that
and not care about the result. But you
can use that keyword await and say,
"Actually, I want to wait until that
completes because
Yeah, so you can always just fire off an
asynchronous operation and not wait for
the result and then keep executing.
Yeah, so what is that similar to what
you'd think of a promise in JavaScript?
Yeah, so Dart didn't always have async
await as native syntax. It used to just
have an API called futures, and if you
ever wanted to do any asynchronous
programming where you were waiting on
file IO or networking or something. What
you would have is like the the low-level
APIs that you would be exposed whenever
you requested something like give me the
the contents of this file, you would get
back a future, which is an object that
you can give it a closure, and it will
invoke the closure later when the value
appears.
And if you did any asynchronous
programming in Dart, that's the API
you're using. You were just dealing with
futures directly. The futures are 95%
identical to promises in JavaScript.
It's a different name for the same
concept and more or less the same API.
Yeah, I've seen those in some docs and
examples.
Okay, what is sound null safety, and why
do we need that in the user interface?
Oh, that's a great question. So, null
safety in general means using the static
type system to keep track of which
variables can contain null and which
ones can't.
And the reason you do that is if you try
to call a method on null, that's going
to throw a null pointer exception in
most languages, and that's bad. It's a
runtime failure.
So, if you have null safety, what you
can do then is the static type system
can prevent those errors. It can tell
you it can basically turn those into
compile errors, where it says, "Hey,
this is a place that you could be
calling a method on null." And it will
make that an error. So, Dart has that. A
few other languages out there have it
now. Sound null safety, when a type
system is sound, what that means is that
the language guarantees that there's no
way for a running program to violate the
rules of the static type system.
So, in the case of null safety, it means
if a variable doesn't allow null,
the type system promises that you will
never ever see null in that variable.
What's nice about that is it means that
the compiler can optimize based on those
assumptions. So, we can use null safety
not just to help find user bugs, but to
generate faster, smaller code, too.
Okay.
But, you also need to know about null
safety when you're doing things. But,
the the GUI is pretty good on Android
Studio.
With the Dart analysis tool, it's pretty
hard to switch off. I've managed to
switch off cuz I haven't had time to
update some of my work.
Yeah.
But, it does complain a lot. Okay, so
what is a spread operator, and is this
unique to Dart?
That's a great question cuz I at
designed the feature that added that to
Dart.
Oh, wow.
So, it's not unique to Dart. So, the
spread operator is a way of inside a
collection literal, like a list literal
or a map literal, something you're
building a a list of stuff. If you
already have another list, and you want
to unpack it in place in that list, the
spread operator does that. It says,
"Okay, take the contents of this inner
list, and kind of unwrap it, and splat
it out in the middle of this new list
that I'm creating." So, it gives you a
really nice short syntax for basically
flattening nested lists. It's not unique
to Dart. JavaScript has them. Ruby, I
think Python does, too. Most of the
scripting languages, you know, either
have them or end up getting it at some
point.
Yeah, it sounds similar to like when you
slice something and put some of it back.
Yeah.
Okay, what is collection if, and again,
is this unique to Dart?
So, collection if and collection for, if
you're going to get to that, they, as
far as I know, they actually are unique
to Dart. And these are three features
that I designed a couple years ago, and
they all work within the context of
collection literals. So, collection if
lets you do something that looks like an
if statement in the middle of like a
list literal or a map literal.
And then basically, when that condition
is true in the in the if, then it will
create the element that is after that
if, right? So, if you have, you know, if
it's Tuesday, you know, add this
element, then only when it's Tuesday do
you get that element in the list. That
doesn't sound super interesting, but it
ends up actually being pretty useful
when you look at Flutter code, because
Flutter builds UI using vanilla Dart
code. It doesn't use a separate template
language or some other declarative
language. A lot of Flutter code is these
very large expressions deeply nested,
containing lots of big list literals,
you know, you know, you'll have lists of
children for many different things. And
it's pretty common to like you know, in
the middle of this big nested ball of
Flutter code be like, "Oh, I actually
only want this button some of the time."
Right? And being able to do an if
directly inside that that list literal
lets you kind of put that logic in there
while keeping the declarative structure
of the surrounding code instead of
having to move that out as like an
imperative like if whatever list.add
this thing, you know?
And is this because
Flutter is a hierarchical tree structure
of widgets? So, certain widgets
would only need to be part of the big
list of widgets if a certain condition.
Right.
Yeah.
Cool. On to the next section. So, this
is number two of the three that's on the
website and it's called productive
development.
So, one of the top things that Dart
lists as a major win is productive
development. So, we're going to explore
that. You've already mentioned this 10
minutes ago, but what is hot reload and
how is that achieved?
So, hot reload is this thing that the
Dart virtual machine supports where you
can make a change to your source code,
body of a function, whatever, and while
the program is running either locally on
your computer or on another device, and
it will update the running application
with your changed code. Right? So, you
can, you know, change the body of a
method and it will replace it in the
running application and then the program
will immediately start executing your
changed code. You don't have to restart
the application and you don't None of
the application state gets reset. So,
imagining, you know, you're work Imagine
you're working on a Flutter app and
you've navigated, you know, 20 screens
deep into some settings UI or something
and then you're like, "Oh, actually
that's the wrong color." You fix the
color, which is some Dart code, and you
immediately get the change in your
running application and you're still on
that same screen, right? Like you don't
have to re-navigate back in.
Yeah, I found that when you're really
breaking your stuff, sometimes you do
have to restart it because you've broken
something way up the chain.
so there's there's restrictions, you
know, if you change the layout of a
class, right? Like adding fields, things
like that, where, you know, existing
memory would potentially get inter-
reinterpreted in strange ways. There's
places where it is too big of a
structural change for it to update it in
place and you have to you know, restart.
You mentioned that that's achieved
because Dart runs in a virtual machine.
Mhm.
Uh we're getting on to another bit. I
don't want to jump too far ahead.
But that's basically how it runs is when
the Dart virtual machine starts and then
loads your code.
Mhm.
Okay. Can we use that hot reload
technique or feature in non-user
interface programs?
It's a good question. I believe so, but
I haven't tried it myself and I don't
know much about it.
I'm thinking about, you know,
in production upgrades of bits and you
don't need to restart the server-side
stuff.
Oh, that's interesting. That's an
interesting use case. I think
how Erlang works.
Yeah, that is like Erlang's bread and
butter, right? Is the ability to hot
patch live executables.
I think we generally think of hot reload
as a development time feature and a
productivity feature and not a
deployment feature.
Yeah, I don't think it would have any
persistence, would it?
Yeah, so I don't know how it persists
and then I don't know if it works in the
context of an optimized build, right? It
may only work in,
you know, development/debug
mode. I could be wrong. This is also not
my area of expertise.
Okay.
So, we've touched about this next bit
slightly when we spoke about dynamic and
static types,
which means Dart has a flexible type
system.
Mhm.
How can a type system be flexible?
Oh, man.
That's a really good question.
So, static type systems, they're
conservative, right? So, a static type
system,
sort of by definition, it will report a
compile error if it thinks that the
program could do something bad at a
particular location. If there is any way
for
a bad thing to happen, that's a compile
error, right? In practice, many programs
are dynamically correct. Like it
wouldn't actually at execution time do
the thing that causes that error, but
the static type system doesn't know
that, right? So static type systems yell
at you about some subset of programs
that actually would be fine if you just
shipped them, right? And that is
frustrating for users, right? Because,
you know, they know their program
actually does run, right? But the static
type system, the compiler won't let them
run it. So being a sort of flexible,
usable static type system means
having the type system's rules
expressive enough
that most of the programs that users
know are correct don't have compile
errors and they're able to run them.
But you could pick and choose between
them or run them together
in your code? So you could opt to say,
right, everything I'm going to do is
going to be static
Yeah, so you could also, you know, try
to have a mixture of static and dynamic
types. So you could have part of your
program just be dynamically typed. And
oh man, there's a long discussion we
could have about that, but there's
there's been a lot of academic research
into different ways to have a mixture of
dynamic and static types in a single
program. There is gradual typing,
optional typing. It gets really, really
complicated and there's a lot of
difficult tradeoffs there. So
But would it come back to what you said
before
with the sound null safety, that if you
thought about everything and did static
types, you could potentially make it
faster for yourself if you profiled it
or
Yeah, so that is part of the tradeoff,
right? So anytime you step outside the
bounds of the static type system and you
rely on dynamic typing, there is a
performance hit, right? There's a reason
that Python and Ruby tend to be slower
than Java and C++, right? And a big part
of that is the static types.
People talk about this a lot, you know,
dynamic versus static. Do you have any
order of magnitudes or numbers? You
know, is this milliseconds slower,
seconds,
hours? Does it just depend on what
you're doing
with that code?
It's a good question. It's
As you get you get worried about all
this stuff, you know,
analysis paralysis as you call it.
Yeah, I mean the the trade-off between
dynamic and static typing is super
complex, right? Because
there are trade-offs at every level,
right? Like there's performance
trade-offs, there's implementation
complexity trade-offs, there's like
ecosystem level trade-offs, there's
learnability trade-offs.
And you know, when a language is
designed, it's designed holistically
around its choice of type system, right?
So, it's not like it's hard to find, you
know, ways to make fair comparisons
about performance between a dynamically
typed language and a statically typed
language because they are different
languages outside of just their type
system, right?
So, there end up being kind of a lot of
confounding factors if you're trying to
just figure out like how much faster is
a static type.
I don't have good numbers, but you know,
I'm confident that static type systems
overall, sound static type systems do
let, you know, compiler authors generate
faster code than dynamically typed ones.
Yeah, I I think you touched upon
some of the other reasons, you know,
like we're thinking about JavaScript and
how popular TypeScript is.
Mhm.
Potentially makes things faster, but
also you don't have to think too much
about, you know, tracing where things
are going because it was this before and
now it's that.
Yeah, there's a whole lot of
productivity improvements when
programming in the large if you have
static type systems, right? Like if you
have types, then it means your IDE has a
much richer understanding of how the
program is connected to each other, you
know, different parts of it are
connected to each other and it can
reflect that back to you, right? You get
code navigation, you know, you get
automated refactoring, you know, you
change the signature of some method and
it will tell you before you run any code
all of the call sites that got broken by
that, right? So, there's a lot of kind
of large-scale maintainability benefits
that you get when you have types.
Cuz you're mainly involved in the
back-end world of it, I suppose.
What's the tooling like for us mortals?
With regards to
rich static analysis, powerful and
configurable tooling, as the website
says.
I think we have a great IDE story. You
know, I spend most of my time writing
Dart code. I use IntelliJ because most
of my stuff is running directly on the
command line, but our static analysis
framework is designed to be pluggable
into a whole bunch of different IDEs. So
it, you know, it works in Android
Studio. We have VS Code integration. I
think there's stuff for Emacs and Vim.
And I think it's solid. I'm pretty
biased and I also, you know, I don't
spend a ton of time in modern Java and
C++ IDEs, but we have all the stuff that
you know and expect, right? Like we
have, you know, a rich set of compiler
errors. We have all the code navigation
you want. Go to definition, find call
sites, all that stuff. We have automated
refactoring.
We have a linting framework that we ship
with and a lot of lints that are based
on static analysis that will help you
find, you know, common mistakes or, you
know, help you write more idiomatic
code. You know, we try to make the
language as productive in your editing
environment, even before you run code,
as we can.
I would totally agree with that. I've
been doing Flutter and Dart for 2 and
1/2 years and
I just like right-clicking and doing
Dart format and
refactoring all of that without having
to think too much.
Yeah, having an automated formatter is
nice.
Yeah, you just go with it.
Um so does it have out of the box
profiling, logging, and debugging as
well?
Yeah, so it ships with the debugger and
you can debug all kinds of Dart
applications, command line, web stuff.
We have
for web developers in Dart, we have two
compilers to JavaScript. One of them
will compile to very optimized,
shippable deployment JavaScript, but
then we have a several one that compiles
to
uh more readable, modular JS that is a
little more debuggable and then also
have source map support so that you can
in your browser step through the Dart
code.
Yeah, we have a nice profiler integrated
with a nice UI for it. So, it will do
flame graphs and all that stuff so you
can see where your time's going.
I've seen that and that's really nice.
And is there something special about
Dart that makes all that easy?
At the language level, not really. You
know, one of the things I find really
interesting about being on a language is
like so much of language success is just
work, right? It's just engineering. You
just like built all the tools and wrote
all the libraries and tested all the
things. And one of the things that's
like a real luxury on the Dart team is
like we have a large amount of like real
deep compiler and VM experts and we've
sunk a lot of time into it, right? So,
we just have, you know, a very mature
JIT, just-in-time compiler, a really
mature VM, debugger, profiler,
ahead-of-time compiler to native code,
extremely mature JavaScript compilers.
Like we've just, you know, we've been
working on the language for about a
decade and we've just we've just sunk a
lot of time into it.
And how many people
work on Dart, do you know?
Oh, man. I don't know.
I think Tim said there's
a lot.
Yes.
I don't know the exact number and if I
did, I don't know if I'm allowed to say
the exact number, but more than a few
and less than a ton.
Yeah, I think he was it was something
around 100 or over or something like
that. It was quite a lot. Is it in the
show public knowledge or I'll dig that
out. Right, I've got to move us on to
the last section, which is the third
benefit on the website which
says fast on all platforms.
Mhm.
So, in this last section, I'd like to
close off the show talking about speed
and how Dart can run on lots of
different platforms.
Oh, boy.
Do you know of a good place to get some
numerical data or public benchmarks or
you know, what do we mean by fast?
Is that frames per second or or what?
How do we understand that?
It is all things. So, one of the things
that's interesting about being a
client-oriented language is that
performance is multi-dimensional, right?
So, we care about throughput, you know,
just how much overall computation can we
do while the program's running, but we
also care about latency, you know, how
much can the program avoid pauses and in
particular garbage collection pauses. We
care about startup time because users
expect client applications to
immediately be responsive. We care about
memory usage. We even care about code
size because download size really does
matter, especially for users in
developing countries where the internet
infrastructure isn't as strong.
Performance for us means like all of
those things.
Okay, and
fast can also also mean productive, you
know, getting going with a fast as well.
And how does it manage to run on lots of
different platforms?
Man, we just did the work.
So, the Dart team was was started by a
bunch of people that were senior people
on the V8 team. V8 is the JavaScript VM
in Chrome and we have, you know, we've
acquired and, you know, built a bigger
team beyond that over the years. So, we
have a lot of people that just have, you
know, decades of experience with virtual
machines, compilers,
and we've just put a lot of time into
it, you know, so it's interesting.
There's if you look around at other
languages,
you can find a lot of languages that
have mature native code compilers, you
know, C++, you know, Swift, you know,
languages like that. And you can find
languages that have pretty mature
compilers to JavaScript like TypeScript,
but there are are fairly few languages
that have mature versions of both of
those. Usually what you see is the
language has a really good native
compiler and a JavaScript compiler that
It kind of a work in progress and it
works, but is maybe not super optimized.
Or the other way around, where the
language is mainly a web language, but
then they're starting to add native
support, you know? And Dart is one of
the few languages where we've we've been
actively working on and maintaining both
of those for about a decade at this
point, so they're they're both just
pretty solid, you know? We've shipped
lots and lots of big apps on them.
Is that because that's what you need,
those platforms, for it to run on, or
this external demand in the community?
Both, you know? So, we Dart's initial
pitch was to be a web language, and our
initial goal was to get browsers to
support a Dart virtual machine natively,
so have them integrate native Dart
support. And to get there, that meant
that we needed to be able to compile to
JavaScript for browsers that didn't have
that support yet. But then we also
wanted a sufficiently sophisticated VM
that it would be compelling to browser
vendors to integrate the VM. So, we
needed to have
both mature, you know, JavaScript
compilers and a mature VM. We ended up
not going down that path for lots and
lots of complicated reasons. But the end
result is that we have pretty mature
compiler technology across a range of
platforms.
Cool. Can Dart be compiled to WASM or
interrupt with it?
Or WASM, however you want to
Ah, that's a really good question. I
don't know the exact current status of
it. I know that we've been researching
it.
We could have a longer discussion about
whether or not targeting WASM is a good
idea versus targeting JavaScript, and
I'm happy to talk about that at length.
But the short answer is that we have put
time and research into compiling to
WASM, but as far as I know, today the
best language to target in a browser is
JavaScript for a language like Dart.
Dart has a garbage collector, so we need
to, you know, if we compile Dart to
WASM, then that means we have to ship a
garbage collector with every
application, and we have to deal with
the interaction between that GC and the
garbage collector in the JavaScript VM.
Whereas if we compile to JavaScript, all
that just works. We essentially get a
really nice mature GC for free.
Yeah, those remind me of a question I
was going to ask when we were talking
about different platforms.
In your experience as a language
developer,
Mhm.
are there differences between garbage
collection across different languages?
Oh, yeah.
That's a thing, right? Like there are
people on this earth that spend their
entire careers becoming garbage
collection experts, and there's just a
wide range of ways to do it. It's like
any interesting technology where
there's no silver bullet. There's no
perfect solution.
There's no standard, is there, for it?
Yeah, there's no standard because every
solution has trade-offs, right? Which
makes it a really interesting field,
right? Because like it That's the kind
of stuff that is fascinating to me
because if Once you can solve it, then
it it loses interest, right? But GCs are
something where like, yeah, there's just
lots of different ways to do it. Each of
them have their pros and cons.
The reason why I asked that is cuz I was
wondering
if it's a choice between do I use a
low-level
even if it has this option to manage my
own memory,
or go for a language that have garbage
collection, but then you have to
actually think how good is that garbage
collection in that language, don't you?
Yeah.
That's interesting.
Yeah, and you know, over time, you know,
I remember when Java came out, and I
was, you know, programming in C and C++
at the time, and, you know, I remember
people being like, yeah, Java's never
going to catch on because like garbage
collection is too slow, right? It'll
just never survive. And that was maybe
true-ish at the time, but GCs have
gotten better and better and better, and
the
you know, the set of programs where GC
is still too slow to be feasible is
getting smaller every day. And these
days, you know, I think
I don't know, 90% of the world's
programs can happily be written in a
garbage collected language and still be
perfectly good from the user's
perspective in terms of like performance
and stuff. And honestly, I love
programming in a managed language,
right? Like that is, you know, from my
experience, probably, you know, top two
or three productivity improvements that
I've ever experienced as a programmer is
just having GC.
So, we touched on AOT before,
ahead-of-time compiling.
Mhm.
How does AOT compile apps to native
machine code for Dart?
Yeah, so, you know, it's funny that we
talk about it as AOT like that is a an
important modifier, but like most users
just think of it as compilation, right?
Like so, you a C compiler, a Rust
compiler, that's doing AOT compilation.
It just means take the program, compile
the whole thing to machine code, and be
done with it, right?
We talk about it as AOT for Dart because
Dart doesn't only have an ahead-of-time
compiler. We also have a just-in-time
compiler, which means it works more
like, you know, JavaScript or scripting
languages where your program you
immediately run from source, and under
the hood it is compiling it to machine
code on the fly.
That's why we can do so many different
things with Dart.
Yeah, that's why we can do things like
hot reload and stuff like that.
And can we build static binaries with
Dart?
Yep. Now we can compile fully to a
fully, you know, native machine code
executable.
And just ship that cloud-native style.
Mhm.
Onto anything.
And I don't need to manage my own
memory.
No, it will include the runtime in it.
You know, you can think of its
compilation model is very similar to Go,
right? Like Go has a garbage collector
and a runtime representation, but it
compiles to a static executable, and
what it does is it just bundles that
entire runtime in with your executable.
And when you ahead-of-time compile the
Dart program, it does the same thing.
So, it just, you know, sticks the GC and
the other machinery needed for object
representation in there.
What tool in the Dart ecosystem creates
JavaScript from Dart code?
So, it ships with the Dart SDK. We have
two compilers to JavaScript. One is
called Dart to JS, very innovative name.
And the other one, I think internally we
tend to call it DDC, but I think Dart
DevC is the external name, and that's
the development compiler. So, Dart to JS
is a whole world optimizing compiler
that tries to make your JavaScript as
small and fast as possible so that you
can deploy it.
And Dart DevC
is more like an incremental modular
debug compiler where it compiles quickly
to fairly readable JavaScript code. So,
while you're iterating on your web app,
you can kind of have a nice fast, you
know, iteration cycle, and you can step
through the code and kind of read it and
figure out what's going on.
So, there's two-part question here
to do with JavaScript. So,
why use Dart when TypeScript exists for
JavaScript's use case? So, if you just
wanted to spit out JavaScript.
And does this mean if I use type safety
and compile to JavaScript, I don't have
to ever use TypeScript?
If that makes sense.
So, the second part is the easier one to
answer. Yes, if you want a statically
typed language that compiles to
JavaScript, you can use Dart, and it
will give you all the benefits of static
types, right? For the former question of
why you might you prefer Dart over
TypeScript or vice versa, I think So,
TypeScript is an incredible language,
and Anders Hejlsberg, the designer is,
you know, one of my heroes.
I've actually never used it. It's just I
know what it is, and I've read about it,
but I've never actually cracked into it.
It's super cool. It's success is well
earned.
So, I think, you know, if users are
happy with TypeScript, I'm happy for
them. If users are happy with Dart, I'm
happy for them. I think TypeScript is an
excellent fit if you already have a
bunch of JavaScript code because
TypeScript makes it very, very easy to
incrementally convert your JavaScript
code over to TypeScript. And it was
designed entirely around that goal,
right? And it it it nails it.
But there are real downsides about that,
right? Which is that because of that,
it's very semantically close to
JavaScript, right? It has this high
affinity. And there's a lot of stuff
about JavaScript that a lot of people
don't like, You know, it it can be
verbose in ways. It has
semantics that can be strange, you know,
things like, you know, loose binding of
this and, you know, the hoisting and
scoping can be weird and it's gotten
better over time, but, you know, there's
a lot of people that don't like
JavaScript and many of the things people
don't like JavaScript are also still
true in TypeScript, right? Because it is
designed to be so seamlessly convertible
from JavaScript. And the other piece of
that is that
taking an idiomatic JavaScript library,
which was not designed for static types,
and applying a type system to it
requires a really sophisticated, rich,
complex static type system.
And if you like types, that's super
cool, right? Like TypeScript has all the
type system features and it's really
interesting, but it's also really
complex. It has a very complicated type
system. It can take a long time to learn
and it can in large programs it can take
a long time to type check just because
there is a lot of machinery going on
under the hood there. The type system
may actually
even be Turing complete.
So, there is a cost there. There's a
cognitive load to a type system of that
level of complexity.
Whereas Dart is more of a sort of clean
slate language, right? Where if you are
starting a new program from scratch and
you want a language that feels like it
was, you know, sort of holistically
designed around static types and it was
designed
in a environment where it could learn
from the mistakes of JavaScript and get
be simpler and easier to understand
because of that, then Dart is a good fit
for that, right? Like I think Dart is a
simpler language, an easier to learn
language, an easier language to fit in
your head.
Cool. I'll just close off this last
section.
I've got a couple of other questions I
think we've got time for as well before
we
wrap up. Do you have any tips for
the hard to define word fast Dart? You
know, is do we always use types for that
or you know,
is there any rules of thumb?
Yeah, so in general, avoiding the
dynamic type is going to help. But for
the most part, your Dart code is already
not using the dynamic type. It's most of
the time using type inference and giving
you the correct static type anyway.
So, you don't usually have to think
about that very much.
I think about my job as a language
designer
as
making the code that feels natural for
you to write be the code that is fast.
Right? Like if I have to spend a lot of
time telling you, "Oh, don't use this
feature even though you wish you could
because it will make your code slow."
Then at some level, like maybe you know,
we're not doing our job right.
And you know, if you talk to like the VM
people and the compiler people,
they will sometimes tell you tips and
tricks of like, "Oh, yeah, this idiom
happens to be slow right now." But I
think overall, they don't want you to
have to, you know, sort of
make your code more convoluted to
satisfy the compiler because their job
is to look at the code that people are
naturally writing and make that code go
fast. Right? So, overall, you know, my
hope is that most users don't have to
think about that too much. Right? Like
write the code that feels simple and
elegant to you,
and our job is to make that be fast
enough. And then use the profiling tools
that we ship with and look for hotspots.
And if you do find hotspots, then in
those places, maybe make your code a
little more verbose or weird in some
patterns to make it faster.
And that just highlights that the tools
are there for when you need to
Yeah.
do the old make it work.
Make it right and make it fast. I think
that's the
Mhm.
Nugget. A couple more questions then
I'll I'll wrap up.
Will Dart ever become a standards-based
language, do you think?
We do have an ECMA standard. I think the
current state of the language is ahead
of the most recent ECMA version of it.
When we initially designed the language,
the original goal was to be a web
language supported natively by browsers,
and that does mean that you need a
standard, right? So, that browsers can
be compatible with each other. So, it
was something that early on we pursued
really strongly. Now that we are not
trying to be natively supported in
browsers, it's relatively less important
for us to have an open third-party
official standard. It's still valuable
and it's still a useful thing to do, but
what users are asking for from us right
now is language velocity, right? They
want us to change the language quickly,
add new features, you know, make the
language more productive for them.
They're asking for that more than
they're asking for standardization.
And that's, you know, kind of how we're
prioritizing. At some point, I could see
us getting to a state where, you know,
if there are multiple independent
implementations of Dart and
compatibility is becoming an issue, then
users will prioritize having an official
standard more than language velocity,
but I don't think it's where we're at in
the life cycle of the language right
now.
Yeah, I suppose that comes down to
someone else is writing a compiler or a
virtual machine, then you have your
standard to work with.
Yeah, and in particular, if you find
yourself in a situation where you have
multiple
competing implementations from
antagonistic companies, you really need
a standard so that you can avoid the
embrace, extend, extinguish failure
mode, right?
But, we're not in that state, so.
Exactly.
Is there any ambitions for Flutter on
the desktop to replace like Electron?
Is that a thing?
That's a good question. I suppose it's a
question of ambitions for whom. You
know, I certainly think that lots of
people on the Dart and Flutter team
hope that we can make desktop support
for Dart compelling enough that people
that would maybe consider Electron for
some apps would end up choosing Dart
instead, and that's that's definitely a
goal. But, you know, in general, like I
don't personally think of myself as a
very competitive person. I like the idea
of just giving people more choices and
options, and you know, what I hope is
that we can make Dart on the desktop
something that
enables some set of people to make
applications that they feel great about.
And if that whether that means more or
fewer electron applications, uh I don't
care too much. I just want to make cool
stuff that lets other people make cool
stuff.
Excellent.
Should anyone be worried about Dart
going away if Google stops Flutter or
something like that? Or is it pretty
long in the tooth now?
Man, this is this is the question that
comes up all the time.
I know. It's always the one with Go or
anything. Yeah. Not maybe Kubernetes
still. But
It's valid, though, right? You know,
it's a valid concern, right? Like when
you are learning a language, there's a
real investment of your time and energy
that you don't get back, right? That you
could have spent investing in some other
ecosystem, right? So, it's totally
reasonable for users to want some
reassurance that their investment is
going to be amortized out over a long
period of time, right? So, I get where
they're coming from. I can't make
promises, but I
you know, every signal that I'm able to
see is that Google cares very much about
Dart. You know, the team is bigger now
than it has ever been. The investment in
Dart is larger now than it's ever been.
We've been around a decade, which is
half of Google's existence, a third of
Google's existence.
Yeah, that's a good point. I forgot
about when people talk about
the age of Go and other things that you
need to put in
Yeah, and Google itself is not that old,
right? Like
That's true. I think that's enough of a
political answer that we can dig into. I
like that. Thank you.
Have you ever really been happy with
your project management tool? Most are
too simple for a growing engineering
team to manage everything or too complex
for anyone to want to use them without
constant product. Shortcut, formerly
known as Clubhouse, is different,
though, because it's worse. Wait, no, we
mean it's better. Shortcut is project
management built specifically for
software teams. It's fast, intuitive,
flexible, powerful, and many other nice
positive adjectives. Let's look at some
highlights. Team-based workflows.
Individual teams can use Shortcut's
default workflows or customize them to
match the way they work or guide goals
and road maps. The work in these
workflows is automatically tied into
larger company goals. It takes one click
to move from a road map to a team's work
to individual updates and vice versa.
Tight VCS integrations. Whether you use
GitHub, GitLab, or Bitbucket, Shortcut
ties directly to them so that you can
update progress from the command line.
The rest of Shortcut is just as keyboard
friendly with their power bar allowing
you to do virtually anything without
touching your mouse. Throw that thing in
the trash. Iterations planning. Set
weekly priorities and then let Shortcut
run the schedule for you with
accompanying burn down charts and other
reporting. Give it a try at
shortcut.com/seradio.
Again, that's shortcut.com/seradio.
Shortcut, again, formerly known as
Clubhouse, because you shouldn't have to
project manage your project management.
All right, let's wrap this up.
So, obviously, Dart is a very powerful
language with a strong, enjoyable
ecosystem.
But, if there's one thing a software
engineer should remember from our show,
what would you like that to be?
I hope that they check out Dart and that
they find that it's a language that's
really enjoyable for them and makes it
fun for them to make applications.
And is there anything
that we missed that you'd like to
mention that you expected to come up?
Nothing that I can think of.
No, I think you did great.
I think we had a good
ad hoc chat about certain things that
came up from a good structure, so I
really enjoyed that. Thank you.
Yeah. Yeah, thanks for having me.
Where can people find out more? We've
got your Twitter account.
Yeah, so dart.dev and flutter.dev are
the main entry points. My Twitter handle
is munificentbob.
Unfortunately, munificent, which is my
GitHub name, was not available on
Twitter.
Whoever that is who got it first.
But, really, dart.dev and flutter.dev
are where you want to go.
Thanks. So, Bob, thanks for coming on
the show. It's been a real pleasure.
This is Gavin Henry for Software
Engineering Radio.
Thank you for listening.
Yeah, thanks for having me.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@SE-Radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.